Hardeep Singh

Residing at No.60, 1st Main, 3rd Cross, J.P Nagar7th Phase Bangalore-560078 Hardeep.singh18@outlook.com

Ph: +917999767208

Profile

Over 4+ years of experience in IT industry with in Configuration Management, Change/Release/Build Management, System Administration, SupportandMaintenance in environments like Kubernetes cluster, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, CentOS and expertise in automating builds and deployment process using Python and Shell scripts with focus on DevOps tools and AWS and Azure Cloud Architecture.

Technical Expertise

Hardware:

Cisco C-series servers, Cisco B-series servers, IBM X-series servers, NetApp 8080, NetApp 8040 storage systems, StorageTek 6000 series SAN array.

Public Cloud Platform:

Azure, Amazon Web Services: Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2), Simple Storage Services (S3), Route 53, Cloud Front, Elastic Bean Stalk, Virtual Private Cloud (VPC), RDS, Cloud Watch, Elastic Load Balancer(ELB), Auto-Scaling, IAM Roles, Users, Profile, Elastic IP's, Nagios, GIT, Security Policies, Cloud Formation.

Operating Systems:

Red hat Linux 4/5/6/7, Windows servers 2003, 2008, 2008 R2, 2012, Windows 7/8/10.

Languages/Technologies:

Bash, Python, HTML, XML, CSS, JavaScript, Kafka

Databases:

Oracle, SQL SERVER, My SQL, MS Sql.

Software/Tools:

Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes, Chef, Ansible, Puppet, Kickstart, Terraform,

Visual Studio:

BI, My SQL, Pager Duty, GitHub, Nagios, Chef, , Ansible, Dynamo DB, , Artifactory, Cloud Watch, NM.

Network Protocols:

TCP/IP, UDP, DHCP, HTTP, VPN, DNS, NTP, FTP, SSH, and Telnet

Application Server:

Apache Tomcat 5.x/7.x, Microsoft Active Directory 2000/2003/2008/2008 R2, DHCP, DNS, WINS

Virtualization:

VSphere 5.0/4.0/4.1, ESX/ESXi server 5.0/4.1/4.0/3.5/3.0. V Sphere Client, VCenter, VMotion, Storage VMotion, VMware Update Manager, VMware Tools, VMware Converter, DRS, HA

DevOps Tools:

Kubernetes, Jenkins, Mesos, GitHub, Orchestrator, Docker and Tomcat.

Monitoring Tool:

New Relic, Sysdig, cloud watch, Graphite, Grafana, Marathon, Mesos

Experience



Current: AgilizTech Software Services Pvt. Limited

Duration: June 2018 to till date Role: Sr. DevOps Engineer http://www.agiliztech.com/

Responsibilities:

- Create and maintain fully automated CI/CD pipelines for code deployment using Bitbucket, Jenkins and Kubernetes.
- Installing, configuring and maintaining Continuous Integration, Automation and Configuration Management tools.
- Built and deployed Docker containers to break up monolithic app into microservices, improving developer workflow, increasing scalability, and optimizing speed
- Experience in working on AWS and its services like AWS IAM, VPC, EC2, ECS, EBS, RDS, S3, Lambda, ELB, Auto Scaling, Route 53, Cloud Front, Cloud Watch, Cloud Trail, SQS, and SNS and experienced in Cloud automation using AWS Cloud Formation templates to create custom sized VPC, subnets, NAT, EC2 instances, ELB and Security groups.
- Strong experience on DevOps essential tools like Chef, Puppet, Ansible, Docker, Kubernetes, GIT, Jenkins, Maven and migrated VMWAREVMs to AWS and Managed Services like EC2, S3, Route53, ELB, EBS.
- Strong experience in AWS, creating, importing and launching volumes, EC2, RDS, Lambda, security groups, auto scaling, load balancers (ELBs), NACL in the defined VPC to design cost effective, fault tolerant and highly available systems.
- Experience maintaining CI environments with build automation tools like Jenkins, Bamboo and TFS and extensively used Jenkins to streamline CI/CD process, automated Master-Slave configurations using temporary slaves.
- Created infrastructure in a coded manner (infrastructure as code) using Puppet, Chef and Ansible

for configuration management of virtual environments, and Vagrant for virtual machine and resource control.

- Deployment of Cloud service including Jenkins and Nexus on Docker using Terraform.
- Worked on AWS opswork, AWS Lambda, AWS code deploys and AWS CloudFormation. Worked on creation of Puppetmanifest files to install tomcat instances and to manage configuration files for multiple applications.
- To achieve Continuous Delivery goal on high scalable environment, used Docker coupled with load-balancing tool Nginx.
- Virtualized the servers using Docker for the test environments and dev-environments needs, also configuration automation using Docker containers.
- Experience in creating Docker Containers leveraging existing Linux Containers and AMI's in addition to creating Docker Containers from scratch.
- Experienced in Installing, upgrading and configuring REDHATLinux 6.x.7.x using KICKSTART Servers.



Current: ANI Technologies Pvt. Ltd. (OLA Cabs)

Duration: October 2017 to till date

Role: DevOps Engineer http://www.olacabs.com/

Responsibilities:

Detailed technical knowledge and hands-on experience of DevOps, Automation, Build Engineering and Configuration Management. Extensive experience in the design and implementation of fully automated Continuous Integration, Continuous Delivery, Continuous Deployment pipelines and DevOps processes

My roles include below:

- Creating fully automated CI build and deployment infrastructure and processes for multiple projects.
- Working closely with Architecture, Development, Test, Security and IT Services teams.
- Installing, configuring and maintaining Continuous Integration, Automation and Configuration Management tools.
- Implementing and developing solutions enabling Development and Operations teams to build, deploy, monitor and test applications and environments
- Implementing monitoring and reporting solutions across a range of environments and platforms
- Mainly Concentrating: EC2 (Elastic load balance) Auto scaling, EBS, VPC, S3, IAM.
- Utilized Cloud Watch to monitor resources such as EC2, CPU Utilization, Amazon RDS DB services, EBS Volumes, to set alarms for notification or automated actions and to monitor logs for better understanding and operation of system.
- Monitored and worked on alerts on various issues such as server availability, Disk issues, CPU Utilization, Processes etc.
- Manage and created user accounts, shared folders, printing services, providing day to day user support, Log management, reporting, applying group policy restrictions etc.
- Provide highly durable and available data by using \$3 data store.
- Using Cloud watch to monitor Traffic behaviour and reacting accordingly
- Providing access to the jump and stage instances through scripts.
- Creating IAM User and providing required permissions.
- Uploading images, files and documents in cloud front
- Checking the spikes and reporting through escalation metrics

Pulling logs for ELB using bash/Python scripts.

Setting up and introducing Continuous Deployment processes and advising on best practice

• Resolving Critical System Issues on a 24 x 7 basis including notification, coordination and dispatch of individuals from various functional groups.



Organization: FOURTH QUADRANT LABS PRIVATE LIMITED

Role: System Engineer

Duration: MAY 2017 to OCTOBER 2017 http://www.fourthquadrantconsult.com

Responsibilities:

I am part of implementation support team (6 members), to provide services like installation, deployment and support of various government/private projects throughout Southern region of India. Part of our job requires designing/redesign/implementing new or existing solutions in on-premises and off-premises infrastructure.

My roles include below:

- Installation of various Cisco/IBM/Dell servers and storages.
- Remote support for servers for existing projects when needed.
- Supporting for migration of existing on-premise infrastructure to cloud.
- Designing new gateway servers and storages to smooth transition of existing data to Glacier.
- Deploying/ Managing/Monitoring/ overall cloud environment on AWS (EC2, ELB, S3, VPC, Cloud Formation, RDS).
- Validating and implementing Continuous Integration tools for deployment.
- Resolving Critical System Issues on a 24 x 7 basis including notification, coordination and dispatch of
 individuals from various functional groups.
- Worked on P1, P2 tickets with customers.
- Worked on providing RCA on issues like (Performance)
- Recommending the best practices for High availability and better performance
- Managing the SLA agreement and handling Escalations
- Assisting the customers with upgrades.
- Performing Log analysis to determine the root cause and finding solutions for the same.
- Collaborating with different vendors like Cisco, Microsoft, to collectively resolve issues.

Projects

Project & Period	Hybrid cloud implementation (Cisco, VMware, AWS)	
Client	Siemens Technology	
Description	Built a hybrid cloud for Siemens technology with co-ordination of Cisco and VMware. Solution used in on-premise data center: Cisco UCS B 9000 series server, VMware ESX 6.0, Red hat Enterprise Linux 7, Ubuntu 16.04 Server and Windows 2016 server. AWS: VPC with public and private virtual gateway, EC2 instances for Kafka, Zookeeper, Radis cluster, Amazon Aurora cluster with region read-replica failover.	
Role and Solution Environment	Acted as Professional Service Engineer to deliver hybrid cloud setup.	



 ${\bf Organization: Hindustan\ Dorr\ Oliver\ Ltd.}$

Duration: June 2015 to April 2017

Role: Assistant Engineer https://www.hdo.in

Responsibilities:

I was a part of Implementation & support for UNIX and storage team of 10 members. We handled different projects of Linux, Storage (Mostly on NetApp/ StorageTek) and Linux. We do planning, designing, implementation, migration and support works.

My roles include below:

- 1. Working closely with development team to bring infrastructure as required.
- 2. Allocate LUN for existing/new systems.
- 3. Capacity planning of storage systems.
- 4. Proactive maintenance of servers, storage and network devices.
- 5. Work on incidents P4, P3 and P2 (Kayoko tickets) based on SLA/OLA.
- 6. Monitoring overall infrastructure using Nagios.

Certifications & Trainings:

Program / Course	Coverage	Duration
Architecting on AWS (Amazon Partner Training)	ILT	3 Days
Linux server administration (RHCSA, RHCE)	ILT	2 Days
Deploying and Managing V-Spear 6.0 (VMware partner Training)	ILT	5 Days
Designing and deploying NetApp storage on UCS (Cisco partner Training Programs)	ILT	5 Days

EDUCATION QUALIFICATIONS:

Qualification	School/college	Board/ University	Year of Passing	percentage% (O.G.P.A)
B.E	Faculty of Eng. & Technology	Annamalai University	2014	8.55
Intermediate	D.A.V Public School	C.B.S.E Board	2010	68.7%
Secondary education	D.A.V Public School	C.B.S.E Board	2008	56.8%

PERSONAL DETAILS:

Name : Hardeep Singh Father's Name : Niranjan Singh

Sex : Male
Marital Status : Single
Nationality : Indian

Hobbies : Reading, Playing cricket, football, PC game,

Languages known : English, Hindi

Mobile : +919424670931, +91799767208 Email : Hardeep.singh18@outlook.com

DECLARATION

I confirm that the information provided by me is true to the best of my knowledge and belief. I request you to please consider my application & give me opportunity to render my best services to the company.

Place: Bangalore

Date: 17 May 2019 [HARDEEP SINGH]